S. Lane Faison papers, 1922-1981, bulk 1950-1976
Archives of American Art
S. Lane Faison papers
1922-1981
bulk 1950-1976
Archives of American Art
Faison, S. Lane (Samson Lane), 1907-2006
AAA.faislane
Archival Resource Key
5.1 Linear feet
The papers of art historian and Monuments Man S. Lane Faison measure 5.1 linear feet and date from 1922 to 1981, bulk from 1950-1976. Faison was an art history professor at Williams College, Massachusetts and, during World War II, he was a member of the Art Looting Intelligence Unit (ALIU) of the U.S. Office of Strategic Services. The collection includes scattered correspondence; writings; teaching files; subject files on exhibitions and projects; artists files; and printed materials. There are two folders of documents and photographs related to Faison's World War II work in the U.S. Art Looting Intelligence Unit.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 6 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Correspondence, 1949-1979 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1, 6 folders)
Series 2: Writings, 1928-1979 (1.7 linear feet; Box 1-2, 7)
Series 3: Teaching Files, 1935-1976 (0.7 linear feet; Box 2-3)
Series 4: Subject Files, 1923-1981 (0.6 linear feet; Box 3, 7)
Series 5: Artist Files, 1922-1976 (1.5 linear feet; Box 3-5, 7)
Series 6: Printed Materials, circa 1935-1980 (0.5 linear feet; Box 6-7)
Biographical / Historical
Samson Lane Faison Jr. (1907-2006) was an art history professor at Williams College and director of the Williams College Museum of Art, Massachusetts. During World War II, Faison served in the Art Looting Investigation Unit of the Office of Strategic Services, an intelligence unit related to the Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Division of the U.S. Army.
Samson Lane Faison Jr. was born in Washington, D.C. on November 16, 1907 to Samson Lane Faison Sr., a brigadier general in the United States Army, and Eleanor Sowers Faison. Faison graduated from Williams College in 1929, completed his M.A. at Harvard University in 1930, and a M.F.A. from Princeton in 1932. Shortly thereafter, he began teaching at Yale as an associate professor of art. In 1935, Faison married Virginia Gordon Weed (d. 1997) and they had four sons: Gordon, George, Christopher and Samson. Faison joined the Williams College faculty in 1936 and became head of the art department in 1940.
During World War II, Faison initially served as an instructor in U.S. Naval Air Force. From 1945-1946, however, Faison was a member of the Office of Strategic Services' Art Looting Investigation Unit (ALIU) responsible for investigating and interrogating Nazis and art dealers who were involved in the systematic looting of fine arts and antiquities across Europe. The ALIU investigated Karl Haberstock, Hitler's primary dealer and Hermann Voss, director of Hitler's Führermuseum in Linz, Austria where Hitler planned to house and display plundered art. Faison was the primary author of the report on the Führermuseum and also interrogated Göring's curator Walter Andreas Hofer. The ALIU issued twelve Detailed Interrogation Reports on Nazi looting activities which were used at the Nuremburg Trials.
During the recovery efforts, the U.S. government decided to ship 202 paintings that had been stolen by the Nazis from several Berlin museums in Germany (notably the Kaiser Friedrich Museum now known as the Bode Museum) to the U.S. for safekeeping at the National Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C. The government argued that the storage conditions in Germany were poor. Twenty-five of the Monuments Men signed a petition, known as the Wiesbaden Manifesto, against moving the paintings out of Germany. The Berlin Paintings were transported to the U.S. anyway and went on display at the National Gallery of Art before being put in storage. Faison was one of ninety-five American art historians who signed a second resolution in protest, demanding the immediate return of the paintings. The artwork, however, was not returned until 1948.
After the war, Faison resumed his professorship and his position as art department chair at Williams College and became director of the Williams College Museum of Art in 1948. In 1950, Faison returned to Germany as the last Director of the Munich Central Collecting Point, one of several recovered artwork repositories in Europe established by the U.S. State Department for inventory, research, and repatriation. Faison's orders were to close down the Munich Collecting Point, which took nine months.
Faison continued to teach at Williams until his retirement. Faison and two of his colleagues, William H. Pierson Jr. and Whitney S. Stoddard, were the three art history professors at Williams College nicknamed the "Holy Trinity," due to their reputation for launching the careers of their students to stratospheric heights. Several of their students went on to become directors at prestigious museums such as the Museum of Modern Art and the Guggenheim in New York, the National Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C. and the Art Institute of Chicago. The New York Times created the moniker "Williams Mafia" in reference to the Williams alumni that were taught by the "Holy Trinity" and whom went on to become prominent members of the art world.
Faison was made a Chevalier of French Legion of Honor in 1952. He received a Guggenheim Fellowship for 1960-1961 and Williams college awarded him a Doctor of Letters in 1971. He stepped down from his position as art department chair in 1969, and retired from his position as the director of the Williams College Museum of Art in 1976. Faison died in Williamstown, MA in 2006 at the age of 98.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The S. Lane Faison papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by S. Lane Faison, Jr. in 4 installments from 1978 to 1982.
Scope and Contents
The papers of art historian and Monuments Man S. Lane Faison measure 5.1 linear feet and date from 1922 to 1981, bulk from 1950-1976. Faison was an art history professor at Williams College, Massachusetts and, during World War II, he was a member of the Art Looting Intelligence Unit (ALIU) of the U.S. Office of Strategic Services. The collection includes scattered correspondence; writings; teaching files; subject files on exhibitions and projects; artists files; and printed materials. There are two folders of documents and photographs related to Faison's World War II work in the U.S. Art Looting Intelligence Unit.
Six folders of scattered correspondence relate to Faison's teaching, lectures, and writings.
Writings include bound student notebooks, lecture notes, typescript drafts, published articles, and material related to his book Handbook of the Collection: Williams College Museum of Art. Eighteen bound notebooks are filled with Faison's college class notes. There are typescript drafts of Faison's articles and speeches, as well as printed versions. Papers relating to Faison's book Handbook of the Collection: Williams College Museum of Art include several drafts, a correction copy, and a folder of illustrations to accompany the text.
Teaching files consist of course files containing miscellaneous notes for classes taught by Faison. The syllabi for classes he taught are filed separately.
Subject files are arranged into three groups: Monuments Men/ALIU files; projects and exhibitions files, and general research files. There are only two folders relating to Faison's World War II work in the ALIU. They contain photographs of looted artwork and documents about the controversial decision to ship recovered artwork to the U.S. for storage in the National Gallery in Washington, D.C. Projects and exhibitions files document Faison's curatorial work on the Oberlin Project (a traveling exhibition of college art) and the Carnegie International Exhibition, and other miscellaneous collaborative projects. Research files contain documents organized according to Faison's original folder headings and include miscellaneous images and clippings loosely grouped together by topic: architecture, advertising, housing, poster design, etc.
Artist files are Faison's documents on specific artists that mostly contain images of artwork, clippings and articles. Artist files were mostly used for teaching and reference.
Printed materials include news clippings, exhibition catalogs, press releases, reports and other miscellaneous materials.
Related Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds an oral history interview of S. Lane Faison conducted on December 14, 1981 by Robert F. Brown for the Archives of American Art's oral history program.
Papers of S. Lane Faison, 1945-1986, are also located at the National Gallery of Art.
Photographs; Art historians -- Massachusetts; World War, 1939-1945 -- Art and the war; Art -- History -- Study and teaching; Carnegie International; Allied Forces. Supreme Headquarters. Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Section; United States. Office of Strategic Services. Art Looting Intelligen Unit; Williams College -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1949-1979; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet 6 folders
  Scope and Contents
  Scattered correspondence is with friends and colleagues about events, classes, lectures and various topics of art history. Most were written during Faison's tenure at Williams College. Several letters are related to the publication of Faison's book the Handbook of a Collection: Williams College Museum of Art.
  Arrangement
  Correspondents with three or more letters have named separate folders. Correspondents with fewer than three letters are arranged chronologically and grouped together in one folder at the end of the subseries.
  - Fox, Milton S., 1951-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Klitzke, Theodore E., 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - de Montebello, Phillipe, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Smith, Gordon M., 1949; 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Smith, Lawrence M.C., 1949-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1949-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Writings, 1928-1979; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Box 1-2, 7
  Faison's writings date from his days as a student and continue through his career as a professor. Found here are eighteen college notebooks, typescript drafts of lectures and articles, and clippings of published articles. There are also typescript drafts, illustrations and a correction copy of his book Handbook of the Collection: Williams College Museum of Art, in addition to a few papers and notes for a book on Manet.
  This series is arranged as 5 subseries:
  Missing Title
  Subseries 2.1: Student Notebooks, 1928-1931
  Subseries 2.2: Lecture Notes, 1946-1976
  Subseries 2.3: Typescript Drafts, circa 1950-1976
  Subseries 2.4: Publications, 1932-1970
  Subseries 2.5: Books, circa 1954, 1978-1979
  - Student Notebooks, 1928-1931; 2.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Honors Work in Art, Vol. I, 1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Honors Work in Art, Vol. II, 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Honors Work in Art, Vol. III, 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Fine Arts II, 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Fine Arts 5c, 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Fine Arts 5b: Renaissance Sculpture, 1929-1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Fine Arts 5f: British Painting, 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Fine Arts 8a: Theory Design, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Fine Arts 9c, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Fine Arts 15 d: Baroque Architecture, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Classical Archaeology 1a, 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Classical Archaeology 1b: Roman, 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Sculpture of the Cinquecento, 1930-1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Art 201, 1930-1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Venetian Painting; Development of Medieval Style, 1930-1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Hellenistic Art, 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Oriental Art, 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Northern Renaissance, 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lecture Notes, 1946-1976; 2.2; Archival Resource Key
    - Impressionists, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - German Tour; Sex in U.S. Art; European Trip, circa 1950-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Dutch Art, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Ideals of American Painting, 1955-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Modern Art: Appearance and Reality, 1957-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Daumier and Corbet, 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Freshman Talk, circa 1960-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Picasso, circa 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Typescript Drafts, circa 1950-1976; bulk 1956-1961; 2.3; Archival Resource Key
    - Transcript for a "Radio Talk on Paul Cezanne", circa 1950-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "The Artist Speaks to His Time", circa 1950-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man", 1957; 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Art, Art History, and the Liberal Arts", 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Fashions in Learning: The History of Art", 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Dedication of William Hayes Ackland Memorial Art Center, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Dedication of the Kresge Art Center, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Dedication of the Colby College Art Center, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Education and the Arts", 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "American Paintings: From the Nourishing Roots", 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "Museum Philosophy", 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "MFA Boston: The Rathbone Years", circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "George Washington and Gilbert Stuart", 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Publications, 1932-1970; 2.4; Archival Resource Key
    - "Barna and Bartolo di Fredi", 1932; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "A Gothic Processional Cross in the Museo Cristiano", 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "A Gothic Reliquary in the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York City", 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Book Reviews by Faison, 1954-1970; 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
      Oversized material housed in Box 7, Folder 1.
    - The Journal of the Walters Art Gallery, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Survivances et Reveils", 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "Fact and Art in Charles Delmuth", 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - "Honore Daumier's Third Class Railway Carriage", circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Art in America foreword, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Smith College Museum of Art Bulletin, 1954-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Apollo, December 1968 Issue, Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Oversized material housed in Box 7, Folder 2.
    - Apollo, December 1969 Issue, Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
      Oversized material housed in Box 7, Folder 3.
    - Oversized Art Bulletin, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Oversized material from Box 2, Folder 27.
    - Oversized Apollo Magazine, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Oversized material from Box 2, Folder 34.
    - Oversized Apollo Magazine, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Oversized material from Box 2, Folder 35.
  - Books, circa 1954; 1978-1979; 2.5; Archival Resource Key
    Found here are documents concerning two books written by Faison. There is one folder relating to a pocket book edition on Édouard Manet written by Faison. The remaining files are on Faison's Handbook of the Collection: Williams College Museum of Art, including three drafts, a compilation of images for publication, and a print edition on which "SLF correction copy" has been written on the cover in ink. None of the drafts for the book are dated..
    - Manet Book Notes, circa 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Typescript Draft 1 for Handbook of the Collection, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Typescript Draft 2 for Handbook of the Collection, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Typescript Draft 3 for Handbook of the Collection, circa 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Illustrations for Handbook of the Collection, circa 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Handbook of the Collection: Williams College Museum of Art, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Teaching Files, 1935-1976; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Teaching files consist of course files and syllabi for classes Faison taught at Williams College. Files contain handwritten notes for lectures, copies of assignments and exam questions, and some miscellaneous printed materials such as images of art, news clippings and articles for reference.
  This series is arranged as 2 subseries:
  Subseries 3.1: Course Files, 1935-1976
  Subseries 3.2: Syllabi, circa 1950-1976
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Course Files, 1935-1976; 3.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Art 2, 1936-circa 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Art 2, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Art 2, circa 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Art 2, circa 1953-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Art 3 - Art 4, circa 1940-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Art 3 - Art 4, circa 1940-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Art 3 - Art 4, circa 1941-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Art 3 - Art 4, circa 1941-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - English - Fine Arts 15-16, circa 1935 -1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - English 1-2, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Art History Charts, 1940-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - History 301, circa 1940-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Art 401, circa 1940-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - History 1A-2A, 1949-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Art 6, circa 1950-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Lists of Slides Used for Lectures, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Art 402, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Syllabi, circa 1950-1976; 3.2; Archival Resource Key
    - Humanities B - Fine Arts, circa 1950-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Art 1, 1954-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Art 3, circa 1955-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Art 4 and Fine Arts S-170: Modern Painting, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - English 20, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Art 303, circa 1960-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Art 201, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Art 7, circa 1961-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Art 552, circa 1961-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Art 304, circa 1964-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Art 363 and Art 263: Nineteenth Century Painting and Sculpture, 1971-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Art 374, formerly Art 304, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Subject Files, 1923-1981; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Box 3, 7
  Subject files contain miscellaneous documents related to Faison's World War II activities and work, special projects and exhibitions, and general research or topics of interest.
  This series is arranged as 3 subseries:
  Subseries 4.1: Monuments Men, 1946-1959, 1970
  Subseries 4.2: Projects & Exhibitions, 1949-1981
  Subseries 4.3: Research Files, 1923-1978
  All the subseries are arranged chronologically, except for research files which are arranged alphabetically.
  - Monuments Men, 1970; 1946-1959; 4.1; Archival Resource Key
    There are only two folders of papers documenting Faison's World War II work in the Art Looting Investigation Unit and related activities. There are documents related to a controversy regarding the shipment to Washington, D.C. of 202 recovered paintings stolen by the Nazis from Berlin museums. The shipment was protested by many prominent art historians, including Faison, who signed a petitition to stop the shipment. The folder includes a press release about the controversy, a list of signers of the resolution, a section of a U.S. State Department bulletin about the return of the paintings, and a few news clippings. The second folder in this subseries contains black and white photographs of what appears to be art looted from the Naples National Gallery by the Nazis for Hermann Göring's personal art collection.
    - Return of German-Owned Art Stored at the National Gallery, 1970; 1946-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Art from Naples National Museum, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
      These photographs were originally in an envelope that contained a note: "Hitler Coll. Goering: Karinhall." This likely indicates that the photographs depict items stolen from the Naples National Museum by Hermann Göring for his personal art collection at his Karinhall residence. One photo IT 42 appears to be missing from the set, but there is an index card with the following annotation that describes what was shown in the photograph: "IT 42 Jewelry: 2 rugs, a chair, Naples Natl. Gallery."
  - Projects & Exhibitions, 1949-1981; 4.2; Archival Resource Key
    Found here are project and exhibition files containing brochures, news clippings, articles, reports, and other assorted materials. There is a file on a television course on the humanities; collaborations with organizations such as the Berkshire Arts Association of which he was a member; and exhibitions he organized, including the Oberlin Project for which Faison was on the planning committee. The Oberlin Project was an exhibition of college-owned art that toured Europe. The Oberlin Project folder includes a few letters from Charles Parkhurst - professor at Oberlin College, Ohio, director of the college museum, and a fellow Monuments Man.
    - Vienna Art Treasures Exhibition, 1949-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Berkshire Art Association, 1954-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - College Museum Traveling Project: Oberlin Project, 1955-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
      Oversized material housed in Box 7, Folder 4.
    - Carnegie International Exhibition, circa 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
      Oversized material housed in Box 7, Folder 5.
    - Council for a Television Course in the Humanities for Secondary Schools, Inc., circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Oversized News Clippings from Box 3, Folder 27, 1955-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Oversized News Clippings from Box 3, Folder 28, circa 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Research Files, 1923-1978; 4.3; Archival Resource Key